<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<database name="ovn-ic-sb" title="OVN Interconnection Southbound Database">
  <p>
    This database holds configuration and state for interconnecting different
    OVN deployments.  The content of the database is populated and used by the
    <code>ovn-ic</code> program in each OVN deployment, and not supposed to be
    directly used by CMS or end user.
  </p>

  <p>
    The OVN Interconnection Southbound database is shared by
    <code>ovn-ic</code> program in each OVN deployment.  It contains
    interconnection information from all related OVN deployments, and is used
    as the intermediate store for each OVN deployment to exchange the
    information.  The <code>ovn-ic</code> program in each deployment is
    responsible for syncing the data between this database and the its own
    northbound and southbound databases.
  </p>

  <h2>Database Structure</h2>

  <p>
    The OVN Interconnection Southbound database contains classes of data with
    different properties, as described in the sections below.
  </p>

  <h3>Availability Zone Specific Information</h3>

  <p>
    These tables contain objects that are availability zone specific.  Each object
    is owned and populated by one availability zone, and read by other availability
    zones.
  </p>

  <p>
    The <ref table="Availability_Zone"/>, <ref table="Gateway"/>, <ref
    table="Encap"/> and <ref table="Port_Binding"/> tables are the availability
    zone specific tables.
  </p>

  <h3>Global Information</h3>

  <p>
    The data that does not belong to any specific availability zone but is
    common for all availability zones.
  </p>

  <p>
    The <ref table="Datapath_Binding"/> table contains the common datapath
    binding information.
  </p>

  <h3>Common Columns</h3>
  <p>
    Each of the tables in this database contains a special column, named
    <code>external_ids</code>.  This column has the same form and purpose each
    place it appears.
  </p>

  <dl>
    <dt><code>external_ids</code>: map of string-string pairs</dt>
    <dd>
      Key-value pairs for use by <code>ovn-ic</code>.
    </dd>
  </dl>
  <table name="IC_SB_Global" title="IC Southbound configuration">
    <p>
      Interconnection Southbound configuration.  This table must have exactly
      one row.
    </p>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      <column name="external_ids">
        See <em>External IDs</em> at the beginning of this document.
      </column>

      <column name="options">
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Connection Options">
      <column name="connections">
        Database clients to which the Open vSwitch database server should
        connect or on which it should listen, along with options for how these
        connections should be configured.  See the <ref table="Connection"/>
        table for more information.
      </column>
      <column name="ssl">
        Global SSL configuration.
      </column>
    </group>
  </table>

  <table name="Availability_Zone" title="Availability Zone Information">
    <p>
      Each row in this table represents an Availability Zone.  Each OVN deployment
      is considered an availability zone from OVN control plane perspective, with
      its own central components, such as northbound and southbound databases and
      <code>ovn-northd</code> daemon.
    </p>

    <column name="name">
      A name that uniquely identifies the availability zone.
    </column>
  </table>

  <table name="Gateway" title="Interconnection Gateway Information">
    <p>
      Each row in this table represents a interconnection gateway chassis in an
      availability zone.
    </p>

    <column name="name">
      The name of the gateway.  See <ref table="Chassis" column="name"/> column
      of the OVN Southbound database's <ref table="Chassis"
      db="OVN_Southbound"/> table.
    </column>

    <column name="availability_zone">
      The availabilty zone that the gateway belongs to.
    </column>

    <column name="hostname">
      The hostname of the gateway.
    </column>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      The overall purpose of these columns is described under <code>Common
      Columns</code> at the beginning of this document.

      <column name="external_ids"/>
    </group>

    <group title="Encapsulation Configuration">
      <p>
        OVN uses encapsulation to transmit logical dataplane packets
        between gateways.
      </p>

      <column name="encaps">
        Points to supported encapsulation configurations to transmit
        logical dataplane packets to this gateway.  Each entry is a <ref
        table="Encap"/> record that describes the configuration.
        See <ref table="Chassis" column="encaps"/> column
        of the OVN Southbound database's <ref table="Chassis"
        db="OVN_Southbound"/> table.
      </column>
    </group>

  </table>

  <table name="Encap" title="Encapsulation Types">
    <p>
      The <ref column="encaps" table="Gateway"/> column in the <ref
      table="Gateway"/> table refers to rows in this table to identify
      how OVN may transmit logical dataplane packets to this gateway.
    </p>

    <column name="type">
      The encapsulation to use to transmit packets to this gateway.
      See <ref table="Encap" column="type"/> column
      of the OVN Southbound database's <ref table="Encap"
      db="OVN_Southbound"/> table.
    </column>

    <column name="options">
      Options for configuring the encapsulation, which may be <ref
      column="type"/> specific.  See <ref table="Encap" column="options"/>
      column of the OVN Southbound database's <ref table="Encap"
      db="OVN_Southbound"/> table.
    </column>

    <column name="ip">
      The IPv4 address of the encapsulation tunnel endpoint.
    </column>

    <column name="gateway_name">
      The name of the gateway that created this encap.
    </column>
  </table>

  <table name="Datapath_Binding" title="Transit Switch Datapath Bindings">
    <p>
      Each row in this table represents a logical datapath for a transit
      logical switch configured in the OVN Interconnection Northbound
      database's <ref table="Transit_Switch" db="OVN_IC_Northbound"/> table.
    </p>

    <column name="transit_switch">
      The name of the transit logical switch that is configured in the OVN
      Interconnection Northbound database's <ref table="Transit_Switch"
      db="OVN_IC_Northbound"/> table.
    </column>

    <column name="tunnel_key">
      <p>
        The tunnel key value to which the logical datapath is bound.  The key
        can be generated by any <code>ovn-ic</code> but the same key is shared
        by all availability zones so that the logical datapaths can be peered
        across them.  A tunnel key for transit switch datapath binding must be
        globally unique.
      </p>

      <p>
        For more information about the meanings of a tunnel key,
        see <ref table="Datapath_Binding" column="tunnel_key"/> column of the OVN
        Southbound database's <ref table="Datapath_Binding" db="OVN_Southbound"/>
        table.
      </p>
    </column>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      The overall purpose of these columns is described under <code>Common
      Columns</code> at the beginning of this document.

      <column name="external_ids"/>
    </group>
  </table>

  <table name="Port_Binding" title="Transit Port Bindings">
    <p>
      Each row in this table binds a logical port on the transit switch to a
      physical gateway and a tunnel key.  Each port on the transit switch
      belongs to a specific availability zone.
    </p>

    <group title="Core Features">
      <column name="transit_switch">
        The name of the transit switch that the corresponding logical port
        belongs to.
      </column>

      <column name="logical_port">
        A logical port, taken from <ref table="Logical_Switch_Port"
        column="name" db="OVN_Northbound"/> in the OVN_Northbound
        database's <ref table="Logical_Switch_Port" db="OVN_Northbound"/>
        table.  The logical port name must be unique across all availability
        zones.
      </column>

      <column name="availability_zone">
        The availability zone that the port belongs to.
      </column>

      <column name="encap">
        Points to supported encapsulation configurations to transmit
        logical dataplane packets to this gateway.  Each entry is a <ref
        table="Encap"/> record that describes the configuration.
      </column>

      <column name="gateway">
        The name of the gateway that this port is physically located.
      </column>

      <column name="tunnel_key">
        <p>
          A number that represents the logical port in the key (e.g. STT key or
          Geneve TLV) field carried within tunnel protocol packets.  The key
          can be generated by any <code>ovn-ic</code> but the same key is
          shared by all availability zones so that the packets can go through
          the datapath pipelines of different availability zones.
        </p>
        <p>
          The tunnel ID must be unique within the scope of a logical datapath.
        </p>
        <p>
          For more information about tunnel key, see <ref table="Port_Binding"
          column="tunnel_key"/> column of the OVN Southbound database's <ref
          table="Port_Binding" db="OVN_Southbound"/> table.
        </p>
      </column>

      <column name="address">
        <p>
          The Ethernet address and IP addresses used by the corresponding logical
          router port peering with the transit switch port.  It is a string combined
          with the value of <ref table="Logical_Router_Port" column="mac"/>
          column followed by the values in <ref table="Logical_Router_Port"
          column="networks"/> column in <ref table="Logical_Router_Port"
          db="OVN_Northbound"/> table.
        </p>
      </column>

    </group>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      <column name="external_ids">
        <p>
          See <em>External IDs</em> at the beginning of this document.
        </p>
      </column>
    </group>
  </table>

  <table name="Route" title="Route">
    <p>
      Each row in this table represents a route advertised.
    </p>

    <group title="Core Features">
      <column name="transit_switch">
        The name of the transit switch, upon which the route is advertised.
      </column>

      <column name="availability_zone">
        The availability zone that has advertised the route.
      </column>

      <column name="ip_prefix">
        IP prefix of this route (e.g. 192.168.100.0/24).
      </column>

      <column name="nexthop">
        Nexthop IP address for this route.
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      <column name="external_ids">
        <p>
          See <em>External IDs</em> at the beginning of this document.
        </p>
      </column>
    </group>
  </table>

  <table name="Connection" title="OVSDB client connections.">
    <p>
      Configuration for a database connection to an Open vSwitch database
      (OVSDB) client.
    </p>

    <p>
      This table primarily configures the Open vSwitch database server
      (<code>ovsdb-server</code>).
    </p>

    <p>
      The Open vSwitch database server can initiate and maintain active
      connections to remote clients.  It can also listen for database
      connections.
    </p>

    <group title="Core Features">
      <column name="target">
        <p>Connection methods for clients.</p>
        <p>
          The following connection methods are currently supported:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt><code>ssl:<var>host</var></code>[<code>:<var>port</var></code>]</dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              The specified SSL <var>port</var> on the given <var>host</var>,
              which can either be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or
              an IP address.  A valid SSL configuration must be provided when
              this form is used, this configuration can be specified via
              command-line options or the <ref table="SSL"/> table.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
            <p>
              SSL support is an optional feature that is not always
              built as part of Open vSwitch.
            </p>
          </dd>

          <dt><code>tcp:<var>host</var></code>[<code>:<var>port</var></code>]</dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              The specified TCP <var>port</var> on the given <var>host</var>,
              which can either be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or
              an IP address (IPv4 or IPv6).  If <var>host</var> is an IPv6
              address, wrap it in square brackets, e.g. <code>tcp:[::1]:6640</code>.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><code>pssl:</code>[<var>port</var>][<code>:<var>host</var></code>]</dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              Listens for SSL connections on the specified TCP <var>port</var>.
              Specify 0 for <var>port</var> to have the kernel automatically
              choose an available port.  If <var>host</var>, which can either
              be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or an IP address,
              is specified, then connections are restricted to the resolved or
              specified local IP address (either IPv4 or IPv6 address).  If
              <var>host</var> is an IPv6 address, wrap in square brackets,
              e.g. <code>pssl:6640:[::1]</code>.  If <var>host</var> is not
              specified then it listens only on IPv4 (but not IPv6) addresses.
              A valid SSL configuration must be provided when this form is used,
              this can be specified either via command-line options or the
              <ref table="SSL"/> table.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
            <p>
              SSL support is an optional feature that is not always built as
              part of Open vSwitch.
            </p>
          </dd>
          <dt><code>ptcp:</code>[<var>port</var>][<code>:<var>host</var></code>]</dt>
          <dd>
            <p>
              Listens for connections on the specified TCP <var>port</var>.
              Specify 0 for <var>port</var> to have the kernel automatically
              choose an available port.  If <var>host</var>, which can either
              be a DNS name (if built with unbound library) or an IP address,
              is specified, then connections are restricted to the resolved or
              specified local IP address (either IPv4 or IPv6 address).  If
              <var>host</var> is an IPv6 address, wrap it in square brackets,
              e.g. <code>ptcp:6640:[::1]</code>.  If <var>host</var> is not
              specified then it listens only on IPv4 addresses.
            </p>
            <p>
              If <var>port</var> is not specified, it defaults to 6640.
            </p>
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>When multiple clients are configured, the <ref column="target"/>
        values must be unique.  Duplicate <ref column="target"/> values yield
        unspecified results.</p>
      </column>

    </group>

    <group title="Client Failure Detection and Handling">
      <column name="max_backoff">
        Maximum number of milliseconds to wait between connection attempts.
        Default is implementation-specific.
      </column>

      <column name="inactivity_probe">
        Maximum number of milliseconds of idle time on connection to the client
        before sending an inactivity probe message.  If Open vSwitch does not
        communicate with the client for the specified number of seconds, it
        will send a probe.  If a response is not received for the same
        additional amount of time, Open vSwitch assumes the connection has been
        broken and attempts to reconnect.  Default is implementation-specific.
        A value of 0 disables inactivity probes.
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Status">
      <p>
        Key-value pair of <ref column="is_connected"/> is always updated.
        Other key-value pairs in the status columns may be updated depends
        on the <ref column="target"/> type.
      </p>

      <p>
        When <ref column="target"/> specifies a connection method that
        listens for inbound connections (e.g. <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>punix:</code>), both <ref column="n_connections"/> and
        <ref column="is_connected"/> may also be updated while the
        remaining key-value pairs are omitted.
      </p>

      <p>
        On the other hand, when <ref column="target"/> specifies an
        outbound connection, all key-value pairs may be updated, except
        the above-mentioned two key-value pairs associated with inbound
        connection targets. They are omitted.
      </p>

      <column name="is_connected">
        <code>true</code> if currently connected to this client,
        <code>false</code> otherwise.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="last_error">
        A human-readable description of the last error on the connection
        to the manager; i.e. <code>strerror(errno)</code>.  This key
        will exist only if an error has occurred.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="state"
              type='{"type": "string", "enum": ["set", ["VOID", "BACKOFF", "CONNECTING", "ACTIVE", "IDLE"]]}'>
        <p>
          The state of the connection to the manager:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt><code>VOID</code></dt>
          <dd>Connection is disabled.</dd>

          <dt><code>BACKOFF</code></dt>
          <dd>Attempting to reconnect at an increasing period.</dd>

          <dt><code>CONNECTING</code></dt>
          <dd>Attempting to connect.</dd>

          <dt><code>ACTIVE</code></dt>
          <dd>Connected, remote host responsive.</dd>

          <dt><code>IDLE</code></dt>
          <dd>Connection is idle.  Waiting for response to keep-alive.</dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          These values may change in the future.  They are provided only for
          human consumption.
        </p>
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="sec_since_connect"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 0}'>
        The amount of time since this client last successfully connected
        to the database (in seconds). Value is empty if client has never
        successfully been connected.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="sec_since_disconnect"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 0}'>
        The amount of time since this client last disconnected from the
        database (in seconds). Value is empty if client has never
        disconnected.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_held">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection
        holds.  Omitted if the connection does not hold any locks.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_waiting">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection is
        currently waiting to acquire.  Omitted if the connection is not waiting
        for any locks.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="locks_lost">
        Space-separated list of the names of OVSDB locks that the connection
        has had stolen by another OVSDB client.  Omitted if no locks have been
        stolen from this connection.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="n_connections"
              type='{"type": "integer", "minInteger": 2}'>
        When <ref column="target"/> specifies a connection method that
        listens for inbound connections (e.g. <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>pssl:</code>) and more than one connection is actually active,
        the value is the number of active connections.  Otherwise, this
        key-value pair is omitted.
      </column>

      <column name="status" key="bound_port" type='{"type": "integer"}'>
        When <ref column="target"/> is <code>ptcp:</code> or
        <code>pssl:</code>, this is the TCP port on which the OVSDB server is
        listening.  (This is particularly useful when <ref
        column="target"/> specifies a port of 0, allowing the kernel to
        choose any available port.)
      </column>
    </group>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      The overall purpose of these columns is described under <code>Common
      Columns</code> at the beginning of this document.

      <column name="external_ids"/>
      <column name="other_config"/>
    </group>
  </table>
  <table name="SSL">
    SSL configuration for ovn-sb database access.

    <column name="private_key">
      Name of a PEM file containing the private key used as the switch's
      identity for SSL connections to the controller.
    </column>

    <column name="certificate">
      Name of a PEM file containing a certificate, signed by the
      certificate authority (CA) used by the controller and manager,
      that certifies the switch's private key, identifying a trustworthy
      switch.
    </column>

    <column name="ca_cert">
      Name of a PEM file containing the CA certificate used to verify
      that the switch is connected to a trustworthy controller.
    </column>

    <column name="bootstrap_ca_cert">
      If set to <code>true</code>, then Open vSwitch will attempt to
      obtain the CA certificate from the controller on its first SSL
      connection and save it to the named PEM file. If it is successful,
      it will immediately drop the connection and reconnect, and from then
      on all SSL connections must be authenticated by a certificate signed
      by the CA certificate thus obtained.  <em>This option exposes the
      SSL connection to a man-in-the-middle attack obtaining the initial
      CA certificate.</em>  It may still be useful for bootstrapping.
    </column>

    <column name="ssl_protocols">
      List of SSL protocols to be enabled for SSL connections. The default
      when this option is omitted is <code>TLSv1,TLSv1.1,TLSv1.2</code>.
    </column>

    <column name="ssl_ciphers">
      List of ciphers (in OpenSSL cipher string format) to be supported
      for SSL connections. The default when this option is omitted is
      <code>HIGH:!aNULL:!MD5</code>.
    </column>

    <group title="Common Columns">
      The overall purpose of these columns is described under <code>Common
      Columns</code> at the beginning of this document.

      <column name="external_ids"/>
    </group>
  </table>

</database>
