<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<manpage program="ovn-sbctl" section="8" title="ovn-sbctl">
    <h1>Name</h1>
    <p>ovn-sbctl -- Open Virtual Network southbound db management utility</p>

    <h1>Synopsis</h1>
    <p><code>ovn-sbctl</code> [<var>options</var>] <var>command</var> [<var>arg</var>...]</p>

    <h1>Description</h1>

    <p>
      The <code>ovn-sbctl</code> program configures the
      <code>OVN_Southbound</code> database by providing a high-level interface
      to its configuration database.  See <code>ovn-sb</code>(5) for
      comprehensive documentation of the database schema.
    </p>

    <p>
      <code>ovn-sbctl</code> connects to an <code>ovsdb-server</code> process
      that maintains an OVN_Southbound configuration database.  Using this
      connection, it queries and possibly applies changes to the database,
      depending on the supplied commands.
    </p>

    <p>
      <code>ovn-sbctl</code> can perform any number of commands in a single
      run, implemented as a single atomic transaction against the database.
    </p>

    <p>
      The <code>ovn-sbctl</code> command line begins with global options (see
      <code>OPTIONS</code> below for details).  The global options are followed
      by one or more commands.  Each command should begin with <code>--</code>
      by itself as a command-line argument, to separate it from the following
      commands.  (The <code>--</code> before the first command is optional.)
      The command itself starts with command-specific options, if any, followed
      by the command name and any arguments.
    </p>

    <h1>Daemon Mode</h1>

    <p>
      When it is invoked in the most ordinary way, <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
      connects to an OVSDB server that hosts the southbound database, retrieves
      a partial copy of the database that is complete enough to do its work,
      sends a transaction request to the server, and receives and processes the
      server's reply.  In common interactive use, this is fine, but if the
      database is large, the step in which <code>ovn-sbctl</code> retrieves a
      partial copy of the database can take a long time, which yields poor
      performance overall.
    </p>

    <p>
      To improve performance in such a case, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> offers a
      "daemon mode," in which the user first starts <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
      running in the background and afterward uses the daemon to execute
      operations.  Over several <code>ovn-sbctl</code> command invocations,
      this performs better overall because it retrieves a copy of the database
      only once at the beginning, not once per program run.
    </p>

    <p>
      Use the <code>--detach</code> option to start an <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
      daemon.  With this option, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> prints the name of a
      control socket to stdout.  The client should save this name in
      environment variable <env>OVN_SB_DAEMON</env>.  Under the Bourne shell
      this might be done like this:
    </p>

    <pre fixed="yes">
      export OVN_SB_DAEMON=$(ovn-sbctl --pidfile --detach)
    </pre>

    <p>
      When <env>OVN_SB_DAEMON</env> is set, <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
      automatically and transparently uses the daemon to execute its commands.
    </p>

    <p>
      When the daemon is no longer needed, kill it and unset the environment
      variable, e.g.:
    </p>

    <pre fixed="yes">
      kill $(cat $OVN_RUNDIR/ovn-sbctl.pid)
      unset OVN_SB_DAEMON
    </pre>

    <p>
      When using daemon mode, an alternative to the <env>OVN_SB_DAEMON</env>
      environment variable is to specify a path for the Unix socket. When
      starting the ovn-sbctl daemon, specify the <code>-u</code> option with a
      full path to the location of the socket file. Here is an exmple:
    </p>

    <pre fixed="yes">
      ovn-sbctl --detach -u /tmp/mysock.ctl
    </pre>

    <p>
      Then to connect to the running daemon, use the <code>-u</code> option
      with the full path to the socket created when the daemon was started:
    </p>

    <pre fixed="yes">
      ovn-sbctl -u /tmp/mysock.ctl show
    </pre>

    <h3>Daemon Commands</h3>

    <p>
      Daemon mode is internally implemented using the same mechanism used by
      <code>ovn-appctl</code>.  One may also use <code>ovn-appctl</code>
      directly with the following commands:
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt>
        <code>run</code> [<var>options</var>] <var>command</var>
        [<var>arg</var>...] [<code>--</code> [<var>options</var>]
        <var>command</var> [<var>arg</var>...] ...]
      </dt>
      <dd>
        Instructs the daemon process to run one or more <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
        commands described above and reply with the results of running these
        commands. Accepts the <code>--no-wait</code>, <code>--wait</code>,
        <code>--timeout</code>, <code>--dry-run</code>, <code>--oneline</code>,
        and the options described under <code>Table Formatting Options</code>
        in addition to the the command-specific options.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>exit</code></dt>
      <dd>Causes <code>ovn-sbctl</code> to gracefully terminate.</dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Options</h1>

    <p>
      The options listed below affect the behavior of <code>ovn-sbctl</code> as
      a whole.  Some individual commands also accept their own options, which
      are given just before the command name.  If the first command on the
      command line has options, then those options must be separated from the
      global options by <code>--</code>.
    </p>

    <p>
      <code>ovn-sbctl</code> also accepts options from the
      <env>OVN_SBCTL_OPTIONS</env> environment variable, in the same format as
      on the command line.  Options from the command line override those in the
      environment.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>--db</code> <var>database</var></dt>
      <dd>
        The OVSDB database remote to contact.  If the <env>OVN_SB_DB</env>
        environment variable is set, its value is used as the default.
        Otherwise, the default is <code>unix:@RUNDIR@/ovnsb_db.sock</code>, but
        this default is unlikely to be useful outside of single-machine OVN
        test environments.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>--leader-only</code></dt>
      <dt><code>--no-leader-only</code></dt>
      <dd>
        By default, or with <code>--leader-only</code>, when the database
        server is a clustered database, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> will avoid
        servers other than the cluster leader.  This ensures that any data that
        <code>ovn-sbctl</code> reads and reports is up-to-date.  With
        <code>--no-leader-only</code>, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> will use any
        server in the cluster, which means that for read-only transactions it
        can report and act on stale data (transactions that modify the database
        are always serialized even with <code>--no-leader-only</code>).  Refer
        to <code>Understanding Cluster Consistency</code> in
        <code>ovsdb</code>(7) for more information.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>--shuffle-remotes</code></dt>
      <dt><code>--no-shuffle-remotes</code></dt>
      <dd>
        By default, or with <code>--shuffle-remotes</code>, when there are
        multiple remotes specified in the OVSDB connection string specified by
        <code>--db</code> or the <env>OVN_SB_DB</env> environment variable, the
        order of the remotes will be shuffled before the client tries to
        connect.  The remotes will be shuffled only once to a new order before
        the first connection attempt.  The following retries, if any, will
        follow the same new order.  The default behavior is to make sure
        clients of a clustered database can distribute evenly to all memembers
        of the cluster.  With <code>--no-shuffle-remotes</code>,
        <code>ovn-sbctl</code> will use the original order specified in the
        connection string to connect.  This allows user to specify the
        preferred order, which is particularly useful for testing.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>--no-syslog</code></dt>
      <dd>
        <p>
          By default, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> logs its arguments and the details
          of any changes that it makes to the system log.  This option disables
          this logging.
        </p>

        <p>
          This option is equivalent to
          <code>--verbose=sbctl:syslog:warn</code>.
        </p>
      </dd>

      <dt><code>--oneline</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Modifies the output format so that the output for each command is
        printed on a single line.  New-line characters that would otherwise
        separate lines are printed as \fB\\n\fR, and any instances of \fB\\\fR
        that would otherwise appear in the output are doubled.  Prints a blank
        line for each command that has no output.  This option does not affect
        the formatting of output from the <code>list</code> or
        <code>find</code> commands; see <code>Table Formatting Options</code>
        below.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>--dry-run</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Prevents <code>ovn-sbctl</code> from actually modifying the database.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>-t <var>secs</var></code></dt>
      <dt><code>--timeout=<var>secs</var></code></dt>
      <dd>
        By default, or with a <var>secs</var> of <code>0</code>,
        <code>ovn-sbctl</code> waits forever for a response from the database.
        This option limits runtime to approximately <var>secs</var> seconds.
        If the timeout expires, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> will exit with a
        <code>SIGALRM</code> signal.  (A timeout would normally happen only if
        the database cannot be contacted, or if the system is overloaded.)
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Daemon Options</h2>
    <xi:include href="lib/daemon.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>Logging options</h2>
    <xi:include href="lib/vlog.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>Table Formatting Options</h2>
    These options control the format of output from the <code>list</code> and
    <code>find</code> commands.
    <xi:include href="lib/table.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>PKI Options</h2>
    <p>
      PKI configuration is required to use SSL for the connection to the
      database.
    </p>
    <xi:include href="lib/ssl.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="lib/ssl-bootstrap.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>Other Options</h2>

    <xi:include href="lib/common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h1>Commands</h1>

    <p>
      The following sections describe the commands that <code>ovn-sbctl</code>
      supports.
    </p>

    <h2>OVN_Southbound Commands</h2>

    <p>
      These commands work with an <code>OVN_Southbound</code> database as a
      whole.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>init</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Initializes the database, if it is empty.  If the database has already
        been initialized, this command has no effect.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>show</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Prints a brief overview of the database contents.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Chassis Commands</h2>

    <p>
      These commands manipulate <code>OVN_Southbound</code> chassis.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt>[<code>--may-exist</code>] <code>chassis-add <var>chassis</var> <var>encap-type</var> <var>encap-ip</var></code></dt>

      <dd>
        <p>
          Creates a new chassis named <var>chassis</var>.
          <var>encap-type</var> is a comma-separated list of tunnel types.  The
          chassis will have one encap entry for each specified tunnel type with
          <var>encap-ip</var> as the destination IP for each.
        </p>

        <p>
          Without \fB\-\-may\-exist\fR, attempting to create a chassis that
          exists is an error.  With \fB\-\-may\-exist\fR, this command does
          nothing if <var>chassis</var> already exists.
        </p>
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--if-exists</code>] <var>chassis-del <var>chassis</var></var></dt>
      <dd>
        <p>
          Deletes <var>chassis</var> and its <var>encaps</var> and
          <var>gateway_ports</var>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Without <code>--if-exists</code>, attempting to delete a chassis that
          does not exist is an error.  With <code>--if-exists</code> attempting
          to delete a chassis that does not exist has no effect.
        </p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Port Binding Commands</h2>

    <p>
      These commands manipulate <code>OVN_Southbound</code> port bindings.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt>[<code>--may-exist</code>] <code>lsp-bind <var>logical-port</var> <var>chassis</var></code></dt>
      <dd>
        <p>
          Binds the logical port named <var>logical-port</var> to
          <var>chassis</var>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Without <code>--may-exist</code>, attempting to bind a logical port
          that has already been bound is an error.  With
          <code>--may-exist</code>, this command does nothing if
          <var>logical-port</var> has already been bound to a chassis.
        </p>
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--if-exists</code>] <code>lsp-unbind <var>logical-port</var></code></dt>
      <dd>
        <p>
          Removes the binding of <var>logical-port</var>.
        </p>

        <p>
          Without <code>--if-exists</code>, attempting to unbind a logical port
          that is not bound is an error.  With <code>--if-exists</code>,
          attempting to unbind logical port that is not bound has no effect.
        </p>
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Logical Flow Commands</h2>

    <dl>
      <dt>[<code>--uuid</code>] [<code>--ovs</code>[<code>=<var>remote</var>]</code>] [<code>--stats</code>] [<code>--vflows</code>] <code>lflow-list</code> [<var>logical-datapath</var>] [<var>lflow</var>...]</dt>

      <dd>
        <p>
          List logical flows.  If <var>logical-datapath</var> is specified,
          only list flows for that logical datapath.  The
          <var>logical-datapath</var> may be given as a UUID or as a datapath
          name (reporting an error if multiple datapaths have the same name).
        </p>

        <p>
          If at least one <var>lflow</var> is given, only matching logical
          flows, if any, are listed.  Each <var>lflow</var> may be specified as
          a UUID or the first few characters of a UUID, optionally prefixed by
          <code>0x</code>.  (Because <code>ovn-controller</code> sets OpenFlow
          flow cookies to the first 32 bits of the corresponding logical flow's
          UUID, this makes it easy to look up the logical flow that generated a
          particular OpenFlow flow.)
        </p>

        <p>
          If <code>--uuid</code> is specified, the output includes the first 32
          bits of each logical flow's UUID.  This makes it easier to find the
          OpenFlow flows that correspond to a given logical flow.
        </p>

        <p>
          If <code>--ovs</code> is included, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> attempts to
          obtain and display the OpenFlow flows that correspond to each OVN
          logical flow.  To do so, <code>ovn-sbctl</code> connects to
          <var>remote</var> (by default,
          <code>unix:@RUNDIR@/br-int.mgmt</code>) over OpenFlow and retrieves
          the flows.  If <var>remote</var> is specified, it must be an active
          OpenFlow connection method described in <code>ovsdb</code>(7).
          Please see the discussion of the similar <code>--ovs</code> option in
          <code>ovn-trace</code>(8) for more information about the OpenFlow
          flow output.
        </p>

        <p>
          By default, OpenFlow flow output includes only match and actions.
          Add <code>--stats</code> to include all OpenFlow information, such as
          packet and byte counters, duration, and timeouts.
        </p>

        <p>
          If <code>--vflows</code> is included, other southbound database
          records directly used for generating OpenFlow flows are also
          listed. This includes: <var>port-bindings</var>,
          <var>mac-bindings</var>, <var>multicast-groups</var>,
          <var>chassis</var>.  The <code>--ovs</code> and <code>--stats</code>
          can also be used in conjunction with <code>--vflows</code>.
        </p>
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--uuid</code>] <code>dump-flows</code> [<var>logical-datapath</var>]</dt>
      <dd>Alias for <code>lflow-list</code>.</dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Remote Connectivity Commands</h2>

    <p>
      These commands manipulate the <code>connections</code> column in the
      <code>SB_Global</code> table and rows in the <code>Connection</code>
      table.  When <code>ovsdb-server</code> is configured to use the
      <code>connections</code> column for OVSDB connections, this allows the
      administrator to use \fBovn\-sbctl\fR to configure database connections.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>get-connection</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Prints the configured connection(s).
      </dd>

      <dt><code>del-connection</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Deletes the configured connection(s).
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--inactivity-probe=</code><var>msecs</var>] <code>set-connection</code> <var>target</var>...</dt>
      <dd>
        Sets the configured manager target or targets.  Use
        <code>--inactivity-probe=</code><var>msecs</var> to override the
        default idle connection inactivity probe time.  Use 0 to disable
        inactivity probes.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>SSL Configuration Commands</h2>
    <p>
      When <code>ovsdb-server</code> is configured to connect using SSL, the
      following parameters are required:
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt><var>private-key</var></dt>
      <dd>
        Specifies a PEM file containing the private key used for SSL
        connections.
      </dd>

      <dt><var>certificate</var></dt>
      <dd>
        Specifies a PEM file containing a certificate, signed by the
        certificate authority (CA) used by the connection peers, that
        certifies the private key, identifying a trustworthy peer.
      </dd>

      <dt><var>ca-cert</var></dt>
      <dd>
        Specifies a PEM file containing the CA certificate used to verify that
        the connection peers are trustworthy.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <p>
      These SSL settings apply to all SSL connections made by the southbound
      database server.
    </p>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>get-ssl</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Prints the SSL configuration.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>del-ssl</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Deletes the current SSL configuration.
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--bootstrap</code>] <code>set-ssl</code>
         <var>private-key</var> <var>certificate</var> <var>ca-cert</var>
         [<var>ssl-protocol-list</var> [<var>ssl-cipher-list</var>]]</dt>
      <dd>
      Sets the SSL configuration.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h2>Database Commands</h2>
    <p>
      These commands query and modify the contents of <code>ovsdb</code>
      tables.  They are a slight abstraction of the <code>ovsdb</code>
      interface and as such they operate at a lower level than other
      <code>ovn-sbctl</code> commands.
    </p>

    <p><var>Identifying Tables, Records, and Columns</var></p>

    <p>
      Each of these commands has a <var>table</var> parameter to identify a
      table within the database.  Many of them also take a <var>record</var>
      parameter that identifies a particular record within a table.  The
      <var>record</var> parameter may be the UUID for a record, which may be
      abbreviated to its first 4 (or more) hex digits, as long as that is
      unique.  Many tables offer additional ways to identify records.  Some
      commands also take <var>column</var> parameters that identify a
      particular field within the records in a table.
    </p>

    <p>
      For a list of tables and their columns, see <code>ovn-sb</code>(5) or
      see the table listing from the <code>--help</code> option.
    </p>

    <p>
      Record names must be specified in full and with correct capitalization,
      except that UUIDs may be abbreviated to their first 4 (or more) hex
      digits, as long as that is unique within the table.  Names of tables and
      columns are not case-sensitive, and <code>-</code> and <code>_</code> are
      treated interchangeably.  Unique abbreviations of table and column names
      are acceptable, e.g. <code>d</code> or <code>dhcp</code> is sufficient
      to identify the <code>DHCP_Options</code> table.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="lib/db-ctl-base.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h1>Environment</h1>

    <dl>
      <dt><env>OVN_SB_DAEMON</env></dt>
      <dd>
        If set, this should name the Unix domain socket for an
        <code>ovn-sbctl</code> server process.  See <code>Daemon Mode</code>,
        above, for more information.
      </dd>

      <dt><env>OVN_SBCTL_OPTIONS</env></dt>
      <dd>
        If set, a set of options for <code>ovn-sbctl</code> to apply
        automatically, in the same form as on the command line.
      </dd>

      <dt><env>OVN_SB_DB</env></dt>
      <dd>
        If set, the default database to contact when the <code>--db</code>
        option is not used.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Exit Status</h1>
    <dl>
      <dt>0</dt>
      <dd>Successful program execution.</dd>

      <dt>1</dt>
      <dd>Usage, syntax, or network error.</dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>See Also</h1>
    <code>ovn-sb</code>(5),
    <code>ovn-appctl</code>(8).

</manpage>
