<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<manpage program="ovn-ic-sbctl" section="8" title="ovn-ic-sbctl">
    <h1>Name</h1>
    <p>ovn-ic-sbctl -- Open Virtual Network interconnection southbound db management utility</p>

    <h1>Synopsis</h1>
    <p><code>ovn-ic-sbctl</code> [<var>options</var>] <var>command</var> [<var>arg</var>...]</p>

    <h1>Description</h1>
    <p>This utility can be used to manage the OVN interconnection southbound database.</p>

    <h1>General Commands</h1>

    <dl>
      <dt><code>init</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Initializes the database, if it is empty.  If the database has already
        been initialized, this command has no effect.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>show [<var>availability_zone</var>]</code></dt>
      <dd>
        Prints a brief overview of the database contents.  If
        <var>availability_zone</var> is provided, only records related to that
        availability zone are shown.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Database Commands</h1>
    <p>These commands query and modify the contents of <code>ovsdb</code> tables.
    They are a slight abstraction of the <code>ovsdb</code> interface and
    as such they operate at a lower level than other <code>ovn-ic-sbctl</code> commands.</p>
    <p><var>Identifying Tables, Records, and Columns</var></p>
    <p>Each of these commands has a <var>table</var> parameter to identify a table
    within the database.  Many of them also take a <var>record</var> parameter
    that identifies a particular record within a table.  The <var>record</var>
    parameter may be the UUID for a record, which may be abbreviated to its
    first 4 (or more) hex digits, as long as that is unique.  Many tables offer
    additional ways to identify records.  Some commands also take
    <var>column</var> parameters that identify a particular field within the
    records in a table.</p>

    <p>
      For a list of tables and their columns, see <code>ovn-ic-sb</code>(5) or
      see the table listing from the <code>--help</code> option.
    </p>

    <p>
      Record names must be specified in full and with correct capitalization,
      except that UUIDs may be abbreviated to their first 4 (or more) hex
      digits, as long as that is unique within the table.  Names of tables and
      columns are not case-sensitive, and <code>-</code> and <code>_</code> are
      treated interchangeably.  Unique abbreviations of table and column names
      are acceptable, e.g. <code>g</code> or <code>gatew</code> is sufficient
      to identify the <code>Gateway</code> table.
    </p>

    <xi:include href="lib/db-ctl-base.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h1>Remote Connectivity Commands</h1>
    <dl>
      <dt><code>get-connection</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Prints the configured connection(s).
      </dd>

      <dt><code>del-connection</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Deletes the configured connection(s).
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--inactivity-probe=</code><var>msecs</var>] <code>set-connection</code> <var>target</var>...</dt>
      <dd>
        Sets the configured manager target or targets.  Use
        <code>--inactivity-probe=</code><var>msecs</var> to override the default
        idle connection inactivity probe time.  Use 0 to disable inactivity probes.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>SSL Configuration Commands</h1>
    <dl>
      <dt><code>get-ssl</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Prints the SSL configuration.
      </dd>

      <dt><code>del-ssl</code></dt>
      <dd>
      Deletes the current SSL configuration.
      </dd>

      <dt>[<code>--bootstrap</code>] <code>set-ssl</code>
         <var>private-key</var> <var>certificate</var> <var>ca-cert</var>
         [<var>ssl-protocol-list</var> [<var>ssl-cipher-list</var>]]</dt>
      <dd>
      Sets the SSL configuration.
      </dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Options</h1>

    <dl>
    <dt><code>--db</code> <var>database</var></dt>
    <dd>
      The OVSDB database remote to contact.  If the <env>OVN_IC_SB_DB</env>
      environment variable is set, its value is used as the default.
      Otherwise, the default is <code>unix:@RUNDIR@/ovn_ic_sb_db.sock</code>, but this
      default is unlikely to be useful outside of single-machine OVN test
      environments.
    </dd>

    <dt><code>--leader-only</code></dt>
    <dt><code>--no-leader-only</code></dt>
    <dd>
      By default, or with <code>--leader-only</code>, when the database server
      is a clustered database, <code>ovn-ic-sbctl</code> will avoid servers other
      than the cluster leader.  This ensures that any data that
      <code>ovn-ic-sbctl</code> reads and reports is up-to-date.  With
      <code>--no-leader-only</code>, <code>ovn-ic-sbctl</code> will use any server
      in the cluster, which means that for read-only transactions it can report
      and act on stale data (transactions that modify the database are always
      serialized even with <code>--no-leader-only</code>).  Refer to
      <code>Understanding Cluster Consistency</code> in <code>ovsdb</code>(7)
      for more information.
    </dd>
    </dl>

    <h1>Logging options</h1>
    <xi:include href="lib/vlog.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h1>Table Formatting Options</h1>
    These options control the format of output from the <code>list</code> and
    <code>find</code> commands.
    <xi:include href="lib/table.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>PKI Options</h2>
    <p>
      PKI configuration is required to use SSL for the connection to the
      database.
    </p>
    <xi:include href="lib/ssl.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>
    <xi:include href="lib/ssl-bootstrap.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

    <h2>Other Options</h2>

    <xi:include href="lib/common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"/>

</manpage>
